Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is ט"ז. Tez Vav.
We're a bit behind, but God willing, we'll get significantly caught up
today, בלי נדר. Bli Neder. Okay, anyway, we pick up on ט"ו
עמוד א' Tes Vav Amud Aleph and we are תא שמע. Tashma.
I'm sorry, yes, תא שמע, Tashma, it's a line starts with the
word שלום Shalom about ten lines down. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
is just still trying to figure out whether בית שמאי Beit Shammai
has adopted the practices of בית הלל Beit Hillel or not, quoted
an interesting statement of רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
that said why not just play it safe and always do חליצה?
Chalitzah? And the גמרא Gemara pointed out that the cost of that
type of a decision, we pointed out the cost that it would
make women אסורה Asurah to the כהנים. Kohanim. The גמרא Gemara pointed
out the cost about the women that were already married and what
the demand of חליצה Chalitzah would do in terms of the emotional
cost and the impact on their marriage and so on, just at
this sort of emotional, relational level, which is obviously something very important
to keep in mind with, you know, because we see a lot
of that today. Well, let's just play it safe. Let's just do
a גירות לחומרא Geyrus Lechumras sometimes, a thing you type of hear
without any consideration of the emotional cost. So anyway, those were some
of the issues we saw yesterday, and we continue now to look
at the question of about whether בית שמאי Beit Shammai adopted the
פסק Psak of בית הלל Beit Hillel or not. תא שמע, Tashma,
which is a question specifically about צרת הבת Tzarat Ha-bat or צרת
ערווה, Tzarat Ervah, but also a more general question in other areas
as well. So תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear, דאמר רבי טרפון,
De'amar Rabbi Tarfon, תאבני Te-avni or תאבני, Te-avani, מתי תבא צרת הבת
לידי ואשאנה. Matai tavo tzarat ha-bat leyadi ve-esena. I have such a
desire, I so much hope that I will have an opportunity to
have a situation of a צרת הבת, Tzarat Ha-bat, which means that
my brother dies without kids, and I happen to have two
wives and one of them is my daughter, that then I can
go ahead and marry the co-wife. So meaning I'd really love to
be able to act on this פסק. Psak. Now רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon was from the house of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So you
see he's expressing a desire, a commitment to act on that פסק.
Psak. So the גמרא Gemara says so you see בית שמאי Beit
Shammai followed their approach. So the גמרא Gemara says אימא ואשיאנה. Eima
va-asena. No, it shouldn't be I want to marry her, it means
when will this scenario happen, not that it'll be about me particularly,
and then I will have an opportunity to, like this is causative,
have her marry out, meaning I'm going to follow בית הלל Beit
Hillel who says that this צרת הבת Tzarat Ha-bat can marry out
without an act of חליצה. Chalitzah. I will marry her to someone
else. So the גמרא Gemara says והא תאבני קאמר, Ve-ha te-avni ka'amar,
it means I desire, why would he be so desirous for this
scenario, especially if he's of the position of, if he's of the
school of בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? So the גמרא Gemara says לאפוקי
מרבי יוחנן בן נורי, Le'apuki me-Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, to come to
reject the idea of רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
that says that we should just play it safe and always do
חליצה, Chalitzah, what we just mentioned. No, I so wish we'll have
this scenario and I'll be able to marry her out without חליצה
Chalitzah and to show that we're just going to do a straight
פסק Psak like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, not even play it safe
like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Of course that's a particularly difficult read
since רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon was of the house of בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, why he would be so invested in that. I do
have to say that as a rabbi who officiates at weddings and
the lack of the use of the causative or the הפעיל Hif'il
in English, you do get into interesting scenarios when you speak about
marrying women. So I once had a woman come up to me
and she said, oh, you remember me, you married me. I said,
no, I actually don't, I think I know who I married, but
anyway. Okay, so difference between ואשאנה Ve-esena and ואשיאנה. Va-asena. All right,
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע, Tashma, come
and hear, דאמר רבי, Rebbe, I'm sorry, we did that. מעשה בבתו
של רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, a story with the daughter of רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, שהייתה נשואה לאבא אחיו, She-hayeta nesua le-Abba achiv, was
married to אבא Abba his brother, an unfortunate name to keep things
straight here, but anyway, we don't really care about his name for
this context. He was married to his brother, the brother of רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel ומית בלא בנים, U-mait belo vanim, and the brother
died without children. וייבם רבן גמליאל את צרתה, Ve-yibem Rabban Gamliel et
tzaratah, and now רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel had a מצוה Mitzvah of
ייבום Yibum with his daughter, but he, and but he did, we
couldn't, she couldn't do, but he did ייבום Yibum with the co-wife.
So here he's acting on the פסק Psak of בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. Okay, so you see that בית שמאי Beit Shammai kept by
their פסק. Psak. So גמרא Gemara says one minute, ותסברה, Ve-tisbarah, does
that make any sense? רבן גמליאל מתלמידי בית שמאי הוא? Rabban Gamliel
mi-talmidei Beit Shammai hu? Who is רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel then of
the students of בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was
from which house? Anybody know?
נשיא, Nasi, descendant of הלל. Hillel.
So of course that's absurd, that can't be the פשט Pshat there.
אלא שאני בתו של רבן גמליאל דאילונית הואי. Ela shani bito shel
Rabban Gamliel de-illanit havai.
So the story was, what the חידוש Chidush wasn't that he was
פוסק Posek בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. The חידוש Chidush was it wasn't
a scenario of צרת ערווה, Tzarat Ervah, his daughter was an אילונית
Illanit and therefore either it was never, she was never, once that
was discovered it turned out she was never married to the guy
because, you know, מקח טעות, Mekach Ta-os, or minimally that there's no,
even if the guy knew about it, there's no מצות ייבום Mitzvat
Yibum by her at all and therefore it was not a scenario
of צרת ערווה. Tzarat Ervah. So then everybody would agree and that
was the חידוש. Chidush. The חידוש Chidush was, was that because of
אילונית Illanit it was not a case of צרת ערווה. Tzarat Ervah.
So גמרא Gemara says one minute, המדקתני סיפא, Ha mi-de-katni seifa, the
end of that ברייתא Baraisa says, אחרים אומרים בתו של רבן גמליאל
אילונית הייתה. Acherim omrim bito shel Rabban Gamliel illanit hayeta. that the
explanation is that his daughter was an אילונית, ilnis, so that that's
a different explanation. מכלל, Michlal, from that you can infer דתנא קמא,
detanna kamma, the original תנא tanna who reported the story without that
point, without that
detail, סבר לאו אילונית היתה, savar lav ilnis hay’sa, is assuming she's
not an אילונית ilnis and nevertheless is saying that he married, that
he did יבום yibum with the צרה. tzara. So the גמרא Gemara
says, היכא דהכיר בה והיכא דלא הכיר בה איכא בינייהו. heicha dehikir
bah veheicha dela hikir bah ika beina'ihu. No, no, no. Everybody agrees
she was an אילונית. ilnis. The question is whether he knew about
it at the outset, the guy who married her or not, the
husband, the original husband. So remember, if he didn't know about it
at the outset and discovered it later, then that's a case where
it was מקח טעות, mekach ta'us, right? Then he never would have
wanted to marry her is the assumption and so on. That's an
obvious case. If he knew about it and married her, and they
definitely were married, then it's not so clear. But then the חידוש
chiddush is that in a case of אילונית ilnis where there can
be no מצוות יבום, mitzvas yibum, there's no הלכה halacha of צרת
ערווה, tzaras ervah, right? But that was debated before, if you remember.
So the תנא קמא tanna kamma assumes the case was where he
discovered that she was an אילונית ilnis and they were never married,
and that made it a simple case. And then אחרים acheirim would
be saying אילונית היתה, ilnis hay’sa, which means it wasn't that she
was discovered, it was always known that she was an אילונית ilnis
and nevertheless, he was able to do יבום yibum because in a
context of אילונית, ilnis, even when it is a good קידושין, kiddushin,
then there is no מצוות יבום mitzvas yibum and there's no case
of צרת ערווה. tzaras ervah. איכא בינייהו. Ika beina'ihu. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אי בעית אימא, ei ba'is eima, now this is always
interesting, you know, when you have an unexplained debate, at least at
the surface it's unexplained, if we say that it's not about בית
שמאי's Beis Shammai position, then it gives the גמרא Gemara an opportunity
to bring in
long-standing debates about the issue and say that's what they're actually debating.
So one case they're debating is the story of an אילונית ilnis
who was married. Does that have a scenario of צרת הבת? tzaras
habas? Or אי בעית אימא, ei ba'is eima, if you want, we
can say a case of כנסה
ולבסוף גירשה איכא בינייהו. kensah u’levasof geirshah ika beina'ihu. Again, a very
important thing that we did quickly, so it's good that it's worth
repeating and we'll see it again. Is there a הלכה halacha of
צרת ערווה tzaras ervah if they were both married to the brother
at the same time, but when the brother died, he was no
longer married to the ערווה? ervah? He had divorced the woman who
was the עריות arayos to the brother. Okay, so do you define
the statuses at the time when the brother was alive and married
to the women? Because to the degree that מצוות יבום mitzvas yibum
is a continuation of the original relationship, you go back to when
that was a live relationship. Or do you look at the statuses
and the מצוות יבום mitzvas yibum only when the brother died? So
let's say there was a scenario here, this man was married to
רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel daughter and the co-wife when he was alive,
but then he divorced רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel daughter. So when he
died and the מצוות יבום mitzvas yibum came about, there was no
ערווה, ervah, there was just the co-wife. So the תנא קמא tanna
kamma holds that's okay, we go by the time of death and
therefore that's why רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel did יבום. yibum. And אחרים
acheirim say, no, no, no, that would not have been sufficient, it
was a different case. It was a case of an אילונית ilnis
and there was never a scenario of co-wife.
I don't know. אי בעית אימא, Ei ba'is eima, and if you
want, I can say יש תנאי בביאה איכא בינייהו, yeish t'nai biviah
ika beina'ihu, which is a very important issue nowadays in discussions of
עגונה, agunah, which is that, but of course,
maybe תנא קמא tanna kamma held the reason that there was no
מצוות יבום, mitzvas yibum, there was no problem of צרת ערווה tzaras
ervah was it was a special case that he had made some
stipulation, I'm only going to marry you under such and such a
condition, and then that was קידושין, kiddushin, then they actually went to
נישואין nisuin and slept together and had sex and so on, and
the question, and then it turned out that the stipulation wasn't satisfied.
Does that undermine the קידושין kiddushin or not? Can you have a
stipulation that makes the marriage dependent, you know, even in a scenario
after they've been living together and having sex together? Maybe the fact
that once they live together, that nullifies any existing condition. So the
תנא קמא tanna kamma said no, the condition is still binding, and
therefore they weren't married, and that's why he could do יבום yibum
to the co-wife. And אחרים acheirim say no, the reason he wasn't
married was because of an אילונית, ilnis, not because of some external
תנאי. t'nai. Okay, many different ways of reading this. Why does it
apply today? Well, because people want to find an approach to dealing
with עגונה agunah issues with תנאי בקידושין t'nai b'kiddushin and make a
stipulation in the קידושין kiddushin based on, you know, what might happen
in the end. But then the question is, does that remain in
effect even after they've been living together? Okay. מתיב רב משארשיא. Masiv
Rav Mesharshiya. So that was a lot of evidence around the case
of צרת ערווה. tzaras ervah. Of course, all the evidence is pointing
to the fact that בית שמאי Beis Shammai held their position. But
the גמרא Gemara gets around it. Now we're going to again go
a little bit afield from the case of צרת ערווה, tzaras ervah,
other types of debate. Does בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position remain viable
or do they wind up just going by the פסק psak of
בית הלל? Beis Hillel? So מתיב רב משארשיא. Masiv Rav Mesharshiya. משארשיא
Mesharshiya asks, מעשה ברבי עקיבא שליקט אתרוג באחד בשבט. ma'aseh be'Rabbi Akiva
sheliket esrog be'echad bi'Shvat. רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, this is a little
bit מעניינא דיומא, me'inyana deyoma, אתרוג esrog at least and maybe we're
coming up eventually to ט"ו בשבט. Tu BiShvat. Okay, so רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva picked an אתרוג esrog on the first of שבט. Shvat.
Now there's a debate of בית הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis
Shammai when the new year of מעשר ma'aser begins. On the first
of שבט Shvat or on ט"ו בשבט. Tu BiShvat. So if, for
example, it's in the שמיטה shmita cycle, it's year two and then
it's becoming
year three. take מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and year three you take
מעשר עני Maaser Oni for the second מעשר. Maaser. Okay so you
picked this אתרוג Esrog in this space in this time so between
ראש חודש שבט Rosh Chodesh Shevat and ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shvat. Is
it a year two אתרוג Esrog or a year three אתרוג? Esrog?
Do you take מעשר עני Maaser Oni or do you take
מעשר שני? Maaser Sheni? מעשר שני Maaser Sheni or מעשר עני? Maaser
Oni? So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel picked it in between these two
times, and the story is ונהג בה בשני עישורין v'nahag bah b'shnei
isurin and he did two separate, two מעשרות, Maasros, after the מעשר
ראשון, Maaser Rishon, אחד כדברי בית שמאי ואחד כדברי בית הלל, echad
k'divrei Beis Shammai v'echad k'divrei Beis Hillel, one following Beis Shammai, one
following Beis Hillel. The גמרא Gemara describes elsewhere
how
he managed
to
do, I mean, because you know, because your מעשר Maaser has to
be your second tenth, not your third tenth. So how he managed
to sort of make stipulations so that the second מעשר Maaser wound
up being, basically he took the second מעשר Maaser as מעשר שני,
Maaser Sheni, then he was פודה podeh it on money, he took
the money and he ate, and he bought food in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
he ate that, that's assuming it was מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. And
in case it was
מעשר עני, Maaser Oni, he took the food that he had just
been פודה, podeh, and he gave it to the עניים. Aniyim. So
he managed to satisfy all the conditions.
(That's what I mean, he would have been done חליצה chalitzah and
יבום).
yibbum Something like that.
Okay so, אחד כדברי בית שמאי ואחד כדברי בית הלל, echad k'divrei
Beis Shammai v'echad k'divrei Beis Hillel, one following Beis Shammai, one following
Beis Hillel. שמע מינה עשו, Shma mina asu, you see that בית
שמאי Beis Shammai maintained their position, because this was רבי עקיבא, Rebbe
Akiva, obviously after the period of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, so בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position was obviously they
didn't back down. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי עקיבא גמרי אסתפקא
ליה, Rebbe Akiva gamrei istapka leh, no no no, רבן גמליאל had
a doubt about his tradition, ולא ידע, v'lo yada, he didn't know
which was בית הלל's Beis Hillel position, אי בית הלל באחד בשבט
אמרו או בט"ו בשבט אמרו. ei Beis Hillel b'echad b'Shevat amru o
b'Tu B'Shvat amru.
He didn't, he wanted to go like בית הלל, Beis Hillel, but
he just didn't know which was בית הלל's Beis Hillel position. So
therefore he was doing both ways because because he didn't know what
was the פסק psak of בית הלל, Beis Hillel, but not because
he was trying to play it safe with a בית שמאי Beis
Shammai פסק. psak. I don't know, maybe but he didn't know if
he could trust their tradition. מתיב מר זוטרא, Mesiv Mar Zutra, so
מר זוטרא Mar Zutra asked, מעשה וילדה, maaseh v'yalda, now here we're
really getting close to עניינא דיומא Inyana d'Yoma at least in the
איסרו חג Isru Chag realm, מעשה וילדה כלתו של שמאי הזקן ופיחת
את המעזיבה וסיכך על גבי מטה בשביל קטן. Maaseh v'yalda kallaso shel
Shammai haZaken u'pichas es ha-maaziva v'sichach al gabei mita bishvil katan.
So there was a story, so the משנה Mishnah says in סוכה
Sukkah that minors who are under the age of חינוך Chinuch or
don't need their don't who still are in need of their mothers
are exempt from סוכה, Sukkah, but here we see that שמאי Shammai
himself was strict about minors, even infants. So his daughter-in-law gave birth,
and he made a hole in the ceiling above, directly above where
the crib was or something, and he put סכך sechach in it,
in order that the infant I guess when he was nursing from
his mother or something, well it's not just about eating, we've made
it just about eating, when he's sleeping should anyway be מקיים mekayem
the מצות סוכה. mitzvas Sukkah. So you see that he's holding by
his position. So שמע מינה עשו, Shma mina asu, you see that
they maintained their position. Of course that's quite funny that שמאי, Shammai,
it's not בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, that's certainly קודם בת קול, kodem
bas kol, anyway. Okay funny that it's bringing, I mean obviously I
don't think it's much of a חידוש chiddush that שמאי Shammai himself
held his position. So anyway the גמרא Gemara says התם הרואה אומר
לאפוקי אוירא עבד. hasam haroeh omer l'afukei avira avad. No,
that's not a problem of אגודות אגודות, agudos agudos, remember that whole
issue here, is it like making factions? Because somebody will say oh
yeah the reason he made he punched a hole in his roof
is he just wanted to he just wanted a yeah and put
סכך sechach on it, he just wanted to ventilate the space. Okay
fine, pretty pretty weak answer. מתיב מר זוטרא, Mesiv Mar Zutra, so
מר זוטרא Mar Zutra asked, מעשה בשוקת יהוא, Maaseh b'shokes Yehu, there
was a story with this like trough, this you know place where
water collected, which was called שוקת יהוא, Shokes Yehu, שהיתה בירושלים, shehayisa
b'Yerushalayim,
which was in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, והיתה נקובה למקוה, v'hayisa nekuva l'mikvah, and
it had a hole which connected it to a מקוה, mikvah, a
collection of rainwater which was a kosher מקוה. mikvah. This itself was
not a kosher מקוה, mikvah, but it was had a hole connecting
it to a kosher מקוה. mikvah. We've discussed this before, how that
makes a מקוה כשרה. mikvah kashera. That's how we do our modern
day מקואות, mikvaos, that you can change the water in the actual
בור bor where they do the where they do the where they
do the טבילה, tevilah, and and you know but you keep the
water, the מקוה mikvah water, in a separate, you know, in a
separate בור, bor, in a separate in a separate space. So anyway
this was the story that they had there. וכל טהרות שהיו בירושלים
נעשו על גבה, v'chol taharos she-hayu b'Yerushalayim naasu al gabah, and all
purifications that they would do in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they would immerse in
this שוקת יהוא, Shokes Yehu, which was a kosher מקוה mikvah because
of its connection with this with this tiny hole to this kosher
מקוה. mikvah. ושלחו בית שמאי
והרחיבוה, v'shalchu Beis Shammai v'hirchivuha, and בית שמאי Beis Shammai sent a
messenger or whatever or message and they made sure that they widened
the hole, שבית שמאי אומרים עד שתיפתח
ברובה, she-Beis Shammai omrim ad she-tipasach b'rubah, that it's not considered a
kosher מקוה mikvah unless it's connected to the kosher מקוה mikvah with
that the division is the majority is is opened up. So you
can't have a small little hole, you need most of the wall
to be removed in order for it to be considered one מקוה
mikvah and to be a kosher מקוה. mikvah. Okay
so ותנן, u'snan, and we learned in a משנה, Mishnah, עירוב מקואות
כשפופרת הנוד, eruv mikvaos k'shfoferes ha-nod, that the actual פסק הלכה psak
halacha is like בית הלל, Beis Hillel, that to combine מקואות, mikvaos,
you only need an opening like a straw that you would put
into a flask, ובעוביו ובחללו, u'v'ovyo u'v'chalalo, its width and its like
you know, whatever, hollow, whatever. the space,
כשתי אצבעות Kishtei Etzbaot like two fingers חוזרות למקומן Chozrot Limkomam that
you would like turn around. So basically it has to be, you
know, a radius of or a, excuse me, a what do you
call it, a diameter of two fingers. Okay, so anyway, so that
was the position. It's obviously a בית הלל Beit Hillel position and
you see that בית שמאי Beit Shammai insisted on his position and
they actually made people change. It wasn't just even for their own
community. Well, maybe for themselves if everybody is using it, they're using
it too. So they wanted to satisfy their own criteria. So the
גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה עשו, Shma mina asu, you see they
maintained their position. And the גמרא Gemara says, התם hasam top of
כ"ו עמוד ב', kaf-vav amud bet, הרואה אומר לאפרושי מייא הוא דקא
בעי. Haroe omer lafrushe mayya hu deka'ave. No, that's not a problem
of אגודות אגודות. agudot agudot. People just figure you want to get
more water into the place and that's why you're making a big
deal about knocking down the wall. Obviously, again, a pretty weak answer.
תא שמע Tashma again, so more and more evidence to prove of
course what we know that בית שמאי Beit Shammai kept their position.
תא שמע דאמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק, Tashma de'amar Rabbi Elazar bar
Tzadok, but the גמרא Gemara has not yet conceded the point. Now
we're moving into a space where it's going to start conceding the
point. Okay, תא שמע דאמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק, Tashma de'amar Rabbi
Elazar bar Tzadok, כשהייתי לומד תורה אצל רבי יוחנן החורני Kshehayiti lomed
Torah etzel Rabbi Yochanan Hachorni as רבי אלעזר בר צדוק Rabbi Elazar
bar Tzadok says when I was learning Torah by רבי יוחנן החורני,
Rabbi Yochanan Hachorni, והייתי שעה אוכל פת חריבה במלח. Ve'iti she'asa ochel
pat chareiva bemela. He was eating very dry bread with salt ובשני
בצורת uvshnei batzoret and it was a time of famine and presumably
he had nothing else to eat. So he's eating a very meager,
meager rations. באתי והודעתי את אבא, Basiti vehodati et abba, I told
my father this, here's the Rebbe I'm learning from, he has nothing
to eat. אמר לי הולך לו זיתים, Amar li holech lo zeitim,
go bring him some olives, you know, send him some olives for
him to eat instead of an apple for the Rebbe, olives for
the Rebbe. Okay, והולכתי לו viholachti lo and I brought it to
him.
ראהן שהן לחים, Ra'asan she'ein lachim, so he apparently looked that he
was going to eat it, but then he saw that they were
wet. אמר לי אינני אוכל זיתים, Amar li einani ochel zeitim, yeah,
I don't like olives. Now the point being because he was very
careful not to eat חולין בטומאה chullin betuma and if olives became
wet by the juice of the olives, then that would be מכשיר
machshir them, make them susceptible to be טמא tamei and he was
afraid that something somebody טמא tamei might have touched them and therefore
he didn't want to eat them. Okay, אמר לי אינני אוכל
זיתים. einani ochel zeitim. באתי והודעתי את אבא, Basiti vehodati et abba,
I told my father what happened. אמר לי לך ואמור לו, Amar
li lech ve'emor lo, go tell him, חבית נקובה הייתה, chavis nekuva
hayita, the barrel that they were in had a hole in it
אלא שסתמוה שמרים, ella shestamua shmarim, but the leaves, like the junk
of the olives, you know, filled up the hole and that's how
come the water collected. Because the point as you might remember is
that liquid only makes something susceptible to טומאה tumah if you want
the liquid. If you completely are not interested in it, it does
not. So if your barrel that you're keeping your olives has a
hole in it, then you don't want the liquid. You want it
all to run off, right? You try to drain it. If, however,
that hole got stopped up, it'll happen that the liquid will collect
and keep the olives wet. But it's not liquid you're interested in
because you put them in a barrel with a hole in it.
So therefore he says that was the scenario. Yes, they got wet,
but don't worry, they're not susceptible because the barrel had a hole
and we wanted the liquid to drain off. Okay, ותנן Vtnan and
we taught in a משנה, Mishna, חבית של זיתים מגולגלים chavis shel
zeitim megulgalim if you had a barrel of like olives that are
compressed, בית שמאי אומרים אין צריכה לנקוב, Beit Shammai omrim ein tzericha
lenakev, you don't have to make a hole because they felt that
the juices that incidentally run off the olives is not even considered
to be a liquid. Okay, it's not olive oil, it's not pressed
olives, it's what's called מוהל, mohal, like the just the water that
runs off the olives, and that's not even a liquid. ובית הלל
אומרים Vibeit Hillel omrim and here בית הלל Beit Hillel is stricter
and they say it is a liquid, it will make the food
susceptible. צריכה לנקוב, Tzericha lenakev, you have to have a hole in
the barrel if you want to avoid the problem. ומודים Umodim but
they agree שאם ניקובה וסתמוה שמרים שהיא טהורה she'im nikuva vesatmua shmarim
shehi tehora if it had a hole and it was filled with
the leaves,
then it is טהורה. tehora. Okay, so that was the case. They
said you don't have to worry, we got a hole in it,
but the hole got stopped up and that's why they're still wet.
ואף על
פי שתלמיד שמאי היה, Ve'af al pi shetalmid Shammai haya, now even
though רבי יוחנן החורני Rabbi Yochanan Hachorni was a student of בית
שמאי, Beit Shammai, a student of שמאי, Shammai, כל מעשיו לא עשה
אלא כדברי בית הלל, kol ma'asav lo asa ela kedivrei Beit Hillel,
he nevertheless always
practiced bottom line like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. And therefore when he
saw they were wet, if he was a student of בית שמאי
Beit Shammai he shouldn't have cared because בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
the liquid doesn't mean anything. The fact that he cared and he
needed the information that there was a hole in the barrel show
that in practice he went like בית הלל. Beit Hillel. So here
you see that he makes a point of going to בית הלל.
Beit Hillel. Now what does that prove about the general? So the
גמרא Gemara says it proves that the general point was the opposite
and that's why this is a חידוש. chiddush. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara says, אי אמרת, I amart, if you say
so, בשלמא עשו Bishlama asu in general the students of שמאי Shammai
followed their own פסק, psak, היינו רבותיה, Hanu revute, that's the חידוש
chiddush of the last line here, that רבי יוחנן החורני Rabbi Yochanan
Hachorni even though he was בית שמאי Beit Shammai made a point
of following בית הלל. Beit Hillel. אלא אי אמרת לא עשו, Ella
i amart lo asu, but if the school of שמאי Shammai never
did their own פסק, psak, they always followed בית הלל, Beit Hillel,
מאי רבותיה, mai revute, what's the חידוש chiddush that he followed בית
הלל? Beit Hillel? Everybody follows בית הלל. Beit Hillel. So the גמרא
Gemara doesn't have an answer to that. It doesn't sort of fully
concede the point, that would have been שמע מינה. shma mina. Like
תא שמע, tashma, when תא שמע tashma ends with
שמע מינה shma mina then... okay, you've proven your point, end of
story. Here it doesn't end that way, but on the face of
it, like it was conclusive, but it didn't rebut it either. On
the face of it, that's pretty good evidence and the evidence is
going to continue. תא שמע, Tasha, come and hear, yes.
Wasn't there, trying to find it, the משנה mishna in סוכה Sukkah
that there's this one guy was sitting with his feet outside eating?
Yes,
right. וזקני בית שמאי V'ziknei Beis Shammai and וזקני בית הלל, v'ziknei
Beis Hillel,
you're right.
I mean, there are a lot of cases where it sounds, it's
a good point, that בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis
Shammai, clearly בית שמאי Beis Shammai clearly maintained, and תוספות Tosafos has
that right at the beginning. Like, what is the גמרא Gemara talking
about? It's clear בית שמאי Beis Shammai maintained their position. So I
don't know what to say. You're right, that's a good point. I
mean, clearly you're remembering because we mentioned the סוכה Sukkah case. But
yeah, it's a good point. תא שמע, Tasha, שאלו את רבי יהושע,
sha'alu es Rabbi Yehoshua, they asked Rabbi Yehoshua. So again, funny, sometimes
we go off topic about בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי
Beis Shammai and sometimes we're focusing specifically on the case of צרת
ערווה, tzaras ervah, which as we know there's more at stake. How
can you allow an intermarriage if you're not all agreeing to the
פסק? psak? תא שמע, Tasha, שאלו את רבי יהושע, sha'alu es Rabbi
Yehoshua, they asked Rabbi Yehoshua, צרת הבת מהו? tzaras habas mahu? What's
the הלכה halacha about a co-wife of a daughter, צרת ערווה, tzaras
ervah, do we, you know, can you, do you do יבום yibum
or do you not do, you know, do you have to do
יבום yibum or חליצה chalitzah and not? Are you allowed to do
יבום? yibum? What's the story? אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to
them, מחלוקת בית שמאי ובית הלל. machlokes Beis Shammai u'Beis Hillel. Okay,
that's a good answer, right? That's what you learn at an early
age. Anybody asks you what's the הלכה, halacha, the answer is it's
a מחלוקת, machlokes, you're almost always right. Okay, so מחלוקת בית שמאי
ובית הלל. machlokes Beis Shammai u'Beis Hillel. So then they said, they
didn't accept that answer. הלכה כדברי מי? halacha k'divrei mi? Shkoach, who
do we פסקן pasken like? So אמר להם, amar lahem, he said
to them, מפני מה אתם מכניסים ראשי בין שני הרים גדולים? mipnei
mah atem machnisim roshi bein shenei harim gedolim? Why are you forcing
me to stick my head between these huge two mountains, בית הלל
Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, בין שתי מחלוקות גדולות, bein
shtei machlokos gedolos, between these two huge debates? Now here the מחלוקת
machlokes can't mean debate because it's not two debates, it's one debate.
So it must mean like these two factions, right? What's the, there's
a word, what's the word, it's not מחלוקת machlokes but מחלקה, machlaka,
right? מחלקה machlaka is a faction, right? What's a מחלקה? machlaka?
A group, it depends on the context.
A group in an inner
department.
Department, department, yeah.
Right, so a group in a, in a bigger group.
Oh, a subgroup. Uh-huh. Okay, but here anyway I think it's מחלקות
גדולות, machlakos gedolos, two big divisions, two big like, you know, two
big factions. בין בית שמאי ובין בית הלל, bein Beis Shammai u'vein
Beis Hillel, you're forcing me between them. So מתירא אני שמא ירוצו
גלגלת ראשי, misyarei ani shema yarutzu gulgeles roshi,
I'm afraid they're going to crush my head. If I come up
with a פסק, psak, the other side's going to attack me, especially
if you get the image that his head, you know, putting the
head between the mountains. If the mountains came together, like it would
be like in a vise, you know, it would crush his head.
Yes.
Didn't רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi generally follow בית הלל? Beis Hillel?
Yes, so anyway, but let's take a look. But he didn't want
to give a פסק. psak. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to say
that the reason he didn't want to be a פסק psak is
because he, if he wanted to פסקן pasken like בית הלל, Beis
Hillel, then he'd basically be saying that all the people in בית
שמאי Beis Shammai who did a case of יבום yibum and צרת
הבת tzaras habas were being עבר over on an איסור כרת issur
kares and all those kids were ממזרים. mamzerim. So I don't want
to go ahead and give a פסק. psak. I'm going to be
telling you that all these kids are ממזרים, mamzerim, so I'm not
going to give an answer to that. Okay, so
of course it's interesting given that the משנה mishna says they wouldn't
hold themselves back from intermarrying. Now the גמרא Gemara dealt with it
by saying they would inform them, etc. But if you take the
פשט pshat of the משנה mishna that everyone in some degree in
some amazing אלו ואלו elu v'elu and pluralistic reality was able to
hold to each other's פסקים, psakim, it would not be so terrible
to פסקן pasken one way if there's an acknowledgment of the validity
of other פסקים. psakim. But this text certainly is not
reflecting that. It would be a huge consequence and I'd get in
big trouble if I gave a פסק. psak. By the way, the
phrase מכניס ראשי, machnis roshi, you know, מכניס ראשי בין שני הרים
גדולים, machnis roshi bein shenei harim gedolim, you find that a lot
in the תשובה teshuva literature when somebody's asked to פסקן pasken an
issue that's been a long-standing debate and debated by some of the
largest הלכתי halachic authorities of previous generations. Often the פוסק posek will
say מי אני להכניס את ראשי בין הרים גדולים, mi ani l'hachnis
es roshi bein harim gedolim, you know, who am I to stick
my head between the huge mountains to give a פסק psak on
something that's already been debated. And then sometimes they'll do it anyway.
Okay, so anyway, okay, so that's what he said. Hold on a
second, this
stupid thing keeps on doing this. I'm sorry, one second.
Okay, all right, so who am I, I'm afraid they're going to
crush my head. אבל אני מעיד לכם, aval ani me'id lachem, I
testify to you על שתי משפחות גדולות שהיו בירושלים, al shtei mishpachos
gedolos she'hayu b'Yerushalayim, there were two big families in
Jerusalem, משפחת בית צבועים מבית עכמאי ומשפחת בית קופאי מבית מקושש. mishpachas
Beis Tzvu'im mi'beis Achmai u'mishpachas Beis Kufa'i mi'beis Mkoshaysh. Okay, so these
two families, שהם בני צרות, she'hem b'nei tzaros, they were descendant from
cases of צרת ערווה tzaras ervah that now, צרת ערווה tzaras ervah
that what? That presumably had married out without
חליצה, chalitzah, seems to be the case, because presumably we're פסקן paskening
like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So ומהם כהנים גדולים ושמשו על גבי
המזבח, u'meihem kohanim gedolim v'shimshu al gabei hamizbe'ach, and from them descendant
כהנים גדולים kohanim gedolim and those that served on the altar. And
therefore, clearly, if it really were a problem, which the גמרא Gemara
will get to, what is the consequence if a צרת ערווה tzaras
ervah or anyone who's obligated in ייבום yibbum marries out without חליצה,
chalitzah, right it's the איסור לאו issur lav of לא תהיה אשת
המת החוצה לאיש זר, lo sihiyeh eshes hameis hachutzah le'ish zar, is
the child פסול לכהונה pasul likhunah or not? We haven't really clarified
that. We're going to clarify that now. But he presumably let's assume
that he that it would be, the child would be פסול לכהונה,
pasul likhunah, so this is evidence that basically of a פסק psak
like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. That would be the way to read
this. I can I'm not going to tell you the answer. I'm
not going to give a פסק. psak. But I can give you
a fact that these families, they were the children of צרת ערוה
tzaaras ervah that married out, and the kids were totally כשר לכהונה.
kasher likhunah. They were even כוהנים גדולים. kohanim gedolim. So figure it
out for yourself. Okay. So obviously that's an evidence that we go
like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אי אמרת בשלמא עשו, Ee amart bishlama asu, if בית שמאי Beis
Shammai is holding of their
position, היינו דקאמר מירתענא, hainu deka'amar mirtana, then he's afraid to give
a פסק psak because בית שמאי Beis Shammai has been following their
position and the consequences of him פוסקנינג paskening like בית הלל Beis
Hillel would be disastrous for בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. אלא אי אמרת
לא עשו, Ella ee amart lo asu, but if בית שמאי Beis
Shammai has not been keeping by their position, אמאי קאמר מירתענא, amai
ka'amar mirtana, what's he afraid of? That everybody anyway is following בית
הלל. Beis Hillel. And the גמרא Gemara doesn't have an answer to
that. And again, a clear other evidence without saying שמע מינה, shma
mina, but clear other evidence that בית שמאי Beis Shammai is is
continuing to hold of their position, and that's why he's afraid to
פוסק. pasken. Now given that, that that's what we're assuming, בית שמאי
Beis Shammai is holding of their position and he's afraid to פוסק,
pasken, the גמרא Gemara still wants to understand the specifics of this
case. So let's take a look. ונהי נמי דעשו, Venei nami de'asu,
fine, let's concede that בית שמאי Beis Shammai is holding their position.
מאי מירתענא, Mai mirtana, why is he afraid? הא אמר רבי יהושע
אין ממזר אלא מחייבי מיתות בית דין. Ha amar Rabbi Yehoshua ein
mamzer ella michayvei misos beis din. This is רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
himself. So it might so even if בית שמאי Beis Shammai is
keeping their position, and he says they're wrong and we go like
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, and when they're doing ייבום yibbum in a
case of צרת ערוה tzaaras ervah it's an איסור כרת issur kares
and the kids are ממזרים. mamzerim. But the גמרא Gemara is saying
the kids aren't ממזרים. mamzerim. I mean we פוסקן pasken they are,
but רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says that you don't have a ממזר
mamzer except for from a from a an act that is forbidden
as a חייב מיתה. chayav misah. חייב מיתה Chayav misah is very
rare. It's basically adultery and the case of like mother, mother-in-law, daughter
and so on, but not the sort of more lateral relationships. So
the גמרא Gemara says, "So go ahead, פוסק pasken like בית הלל.
Beis Hillel. What are you afraid of? You're not saying the kids
of בית שמאי Beis Shammai are ממזרים. mamzerim. You yourself hold that
they wouldn't be ממזרים mamzerim in that case. Now maybe they בית
שמאי Beis Shammai hold they would be, but okay. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. ונהי נמי דממזר לא הוי, Venei nami
demamzer lo havi, fine, he wouldn't be saying they're ממזר, mamzer, פגום
מיהא הוי, pagum meiha havi, but at least they would be פגום,
pagum, which means אסור לכהונה, asur likhunah, מקל וחומר מאלמנה. mikal vachomer
me'almanah. We make a קל וחומר kal vachomer from the case of
an אלמנה almanah to a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. An אלמנה almanah
with a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, we know that not only is
she אסורה, asurah, but if there's a child that results from that,
that the child is פסול pasul to all כהונה, kehunah, even for
normal כוהנים. kohanim. So we can make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
מה אלמנה שאין איסורה נוהג בכל, Mah almanah she'ein issurah noheig bakol,
by the case of a widow, it does not apply to all
people, not even all כוהנים, kohanim, only a כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
בנה
פגום, Binah pagum, the child that results from that
act, פגום pagum is
like... and yeah but there's what, what? Tainted? Tainted. Yeah, but
there's a good English word though, stigmatized. Okay, so the child is
stigmatized, so maybe that's a little too much suggest a social stigma.
Anyway, okay, anyway, so בנה פגום, binah pagum, the child is forbidden
to other כוהנים kohanim so because it resulted from that union. זו,
Zu, this woman who is an איסור ערוה, issur ervah, שאיסורה שווה
בכל, she'issurah shaveh bakol, that it applies to all people that she's
an ערוה ervah to, certainly the child even if not a ממזר
mamzer would be אסור asur to כוהנים. kohanim. So even
within רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua own פסק psak that the child is
not a ממזר, mamzer, there's still a huge consequence פוסקנינג paskening like
בית הלל Beis Hillel for בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, and therefore he
did not want to פוסק pasken it. Again, though, evidence that בית
שמאי Beis Shammai is keeping to their פסק. psak. Yes.
I want to ask this with the following. It's like the רמב"ם
Rambam for example suggests says outright that in the good old days
there would be no מחלוקת, machlokes, right? There's a sort of a
corrupt
עד שרבו תלמידי בית הלל בית שמאי. ad sherabu talmidei Beis Hillel
Beis Shammai.
So so was that a חידוש chiddush of the רמב"ם Rambam that
we subscribe to? In other words, every every משנה אבות, Mishna Avos,
yeah.
No, I understand, but in other words, there's
such richness in the diversity of opinion, still underlying the whole thing
is sort of the sense that it's negative that there's such a
culture of מחלוקת. machlokes. That's a different question. No, the רמב"ם Rambam
is not the one that says
that the מחלוקת machlokes was מרבה בישראל marbeh b'Yisrael in the time
of בית הלל ובית שמאי. Beis Hillel uBeis Shammai. The question is
to what degree do you view that as a negative or not?
Which is a different question, which is interesting, since the רמב"ם Rambam
understands that the source of מחלוקת machlokes is not different traditions, is
not error, but the source of מחלוקת machlokes is just is just
the reality when a human mind encounters a text you're going to
come up with different types of reads and so on, and there's
not one predetermined truth that we're all trying to find, but it's
the process of interpretation. So you could דוקא davka say that's a
good reason to say that מחלוקת machlokes isn't a bad thing. So
it is interesting that רמב"ם Rambam does frame it that way. Yes.
Okay, but moving on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
פסקן, pasken, so okay, so now the גמרא Gemara has another question,
but again it's evidence that בית שמאי Beis Shammai is holding of
their position. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, קא בעו מיניה
צרות וקא פשיט ליה בני צרות. ka ba'u minei tzaros veka pashit
lei benei tzaros. They asked him what's the הלכה halacha about the
co-wives, why is he talking about the children of the co-wives? Now,
obviously part, the simple answer is because from the fact that how
we deal with the children shows you can infer something about how
we understand the status of the co-wives, but let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So תרתי קא בעו מיניה, tarti ka ba'u minei,
they asked two questions. Number one, צרות מאי, tzaros mai, what's the
story of the co-wives? Do we פסקן pasken like בית הלל? Beis
Hillel? Do they need חליצה? chalitza? I mean, like בית הלל Beis
Hillel that they don't need חליצה chalitza or do we have to
be חושש choshesh like בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? ואם תמצא לומר צרת
כבית הלל, veim timtza lomar tzaras keveis Hillel, and if you say
like בית הלל Beis Hillel and they can marry out without חליצה,
chalitza, so בני צרת דבית הלל לבית שמאי מאי הוו, benei tzaras
deveis Hillel leveis Shammai mai havu, what would בית שמאי Beis Shammai
think of those scenarios? Meaning, what would בית שמאי Beis Shammai think
about the co-wives that married out without חליצה? chalitza? What would the
status of their children be? So the גמרא Gemara says, למאי נפקא
מינה, lemai nafka mina, what difference would it make? למפשט ולד מחזיר
גרושתו לבית הלל, limpashat vlad machzir gerushaso leveis Hillel, because we want
to in general know, what is the status of a child of
a union which is an איסור לאו? issur lav? Okay, so one
type of an איסור לאו issur lav is the יבמה yevama that
marries somebody outside without חליצה. chalitza. Another classic איסור לאו issur lav
the גמרא Gemara deals with that's not related to כהנים, Kohanim, by
the way, is מחזיר גרושתו, machzir gerushaso, a man who remarries a
woman who he divorced and who married somebody else. Okay, and the
question is, is the child of איסורי לאו issurei lav that are
not איסורי כהונה, issurei kehuna, right, those are hard to find, איסורי
לאו issurei lav that are not איסורי כהונה, issurei kehuna, are those
children אסור assur to כהנים Kohanim or not? So we therefore want
to know, what would be the story of the children of the
case of a צרת ערווה tzaras erva from בית שמאי's Beis Shammai
perspective? She wasn't allowed to marry out and she did, would the
children be אסור assur or מותר muttar to the כהן? Kohen? And
the other relevance of that question is the case of מחזיר גרושתו.
machzir gerushaso. What's the story with their children? So the גמרא Gemara
says, מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
a קל וחומר kal vachomer like we said before, ומה אלמנה לכהן
גדול שאין איסורה שוה בכל בנה פגום, u'ma almana lechohen gadol she'ein
issura shaveh bakol bena pagum, the child of an אלמנה almana and
a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the child, even though that's a very
limited איסור, issur, the child is forbidden to כהנים, Kohanim, זו שאיסורה
שוה בכל, zu she'issura shaveh bakol, this case about a woman who
marries outside without חליצה chalitza or מחזיר גרושתו machzir gerushaso that it
applies to all people, אינו דין שבנה פגום, eino din shebena pagum,
how much more so should the child be פגום, pagum, stigmatized and
אסור assur to כהנים? Kohanim? או דילמא, o dilma, or do we
say, איכא למפרך, ika lemifrach, you can challenge this. מה לאלמנה שהיא
עצמה מתחללת, ma le'almana shehi atzma mitchalleles, by the case of an
אלמנה, almana, when an אלמנה almana has sex with a כהן, Kohen,
she herself becomes a חללה. chalala. And part of the way the
mechanism of פסול כהונה psul kehuna works is that the act of
forbidden sex makes the woman also a חללה. chalala. Now, you'll say
well she's already אסור, assur, no but she's only אסור assur to
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So here she has sex with a
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, she would not have been אסור assur to
a כהן. Kohen. But the act of forbidden sex, particularly in the
context of when it violates the איסורי כהונה issurei kehuna about unions,
makes the woman a חללה chalala and makes the child a חללה.
chalala. And to some degree it's even seen that the status of
the child might be somehow derivative of the fact that that act
made the mother a חללה. chalala. So therefore that's what the גמרא
Gemara is saying. Fine, that's אלמנה לכהן גדול, almana lechohen gadol, that's
specifically איסורי כהונה. issurei kehuna. In a context of sex that's אסור
assur because of the דינים dinim of כהונה kehuna and with a
כהן, Kohen, then it makes the woman a חללה chalala and it
makes the child a חללה chalala either. The case of מחזיר גרושתו
machzir gerushaso or a woman who is a יבמה לשוק, yevama lashuk,
those cases is not about an איסור issur relating to כהנים, Kohanim,
doesn't have the whole idea of her becoming a חללה, chalala, and
therefore doesn't make the child a חללה chalala either. So that was
the question. What's the story about the צרות? tzaros? What's the story
about the kids, what would בית שמאי Beis Shammai say about the
kids? So ואמר להו צרות מצער אני, veamar lehu tzaros mitzaer ani,
as far as the צרות tzaros is concerned, I recuse myself, I'm
not going to give you an answer to that. I'm afraid to
give you a פסק. psak. בני צרות, benei tzaros, but what you
should know is that the children of those, so אני מעיד לכם,
ani meid lachem, I testify to you, meaning, so as opposed to
what I said which I still think is פשט, pshat, is that
what he was sort of saying is I'm not going to tell
you the answer but figure it out for yourself because the בני
צרות benei tzaros are כהנים, Kohanim, so clearly it wasn't a problem,
clearly we פסקן pasken like בית הלל. Beis Hillel. The גמרא Gemara
is not reading it that way. The גמרא Gemara is reading what
he's saying is, I'm not going to give you a פסק psak
about בני צרות, benei tzaros, but either way what you should know
is that I'm not going to give you a פסק psak about
צרה, tzara, but what you should know is that the בני צרות
benei tzaros who married out without חליצה, chalitza, they are not a
problem. Even בית שמאי Beis Shammai would concede they're not a problem,
and here we have these big families and they became כהנים, Kohanim,
so you should at least know that even those that practiced like
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, the children are not a problem for בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. Okay, so that's the end of that story. But
again, it's clear evidence that בית שמאי Beis Shammai kept their position.
תא שמע, ta shema, we're going to try again and now, again,
the evidence is more and more piling up. Top of טו עמוד
א. tes-vav amud aleph. בימי רבי דוסא בן הרכינס, bimei Rabbi Dosa
ben Hurkinas, in the time of רבי דוסא בן הרכינס, Rabbi Dosa
ben Hurkinas, הותרה צרת הבת לאחים, husra tzaras habas la'achim, somebody basically
פסקן pasken and we're going to see it sounds like this. So
the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה, shema mina, finally שמע מינה. shema
mina. Here's a black and white statement that somebody פסקנד paskened להתיר
lemattir the case of צרת ערוה tzaras ervah to do יבום, yibum,
clearly people are still holding of the position of בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. Okay, and therefore the way בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית
שמאי Beit Shammai intermarried was not because בית שמאי Beit Shammai wound
up acting like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, but because of some other
explanation. Either because they would inform if there was a problem so
they could assume
there wasn't a problem if they weren't saying anything, or other such
answers as we've seen before. Now, it was either before or after.
Again, it was true, he was early, but the גמרא Gemara is
not necessarily saying it matters. Okay, it's said the question is both
before and after. גופא. Gufa. Now let's look at this story. Okay,
so we're finally done with that question. Yes, בית שמאי Beit Shammai
held by their guns. Now let's look at this fascinating story about
the פסק psak like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. בימי רבי דוסא בן
הרכינס התירו צרת הבת לאחים. Bimei Rabbi Dosa ben Horkinas hitiru tzorat
habat leachim. In his time, they had permitted the צרת הבת tzorat
habat to the brothers, a case of צרת ערוה tzaras ervah with
יבום, yibum, like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. And they assumed it was
רבי דוסא בן הרכינס. Rabbi Dosa ben Horkinas. והיה הדבר קשה לחכמים,
Vehaya hadavar kasha lachachamim, and the matter was very distressing to the
חכמים Chachamim that there was a פסק psak that they thought דוסא
בן הרכינס Dosa ben Horkinas had issued like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
מפני שחכם גדול היה, mipnei shechacham gadol haya, because he was a
huge sage and they were like, you know, they were obviously deferential
to his authority but they strongly disagreed with this פסק. psak. ועיניו
קמו מלבא לבית המדרש, Veeinav kamu milavo lebeit hamidrash, and his eyes
had literally stood, but meaning had grown dim, he had lost his
eyesight or he was getting blind and he no longer came to
the בית המדרש. Beit HaMidrash. So also maybe they felt that they
weren't in an opportunity to discuss the matter with him. Maybe also
they were afraid that led him to being more independent, he wasn't
being there in the, you know, in the בית המדרש Beit HaMidrash
discussing the issue with the colleagues, but they needed to raise this
issue with him because he was doing what they considered to be
a renegade פסק. psak. Okay, so how are they going to deal
with it? The word is plural, I don't understand, עיניו, einav, עינים.
einayim. No, no, no, התירו. hitiiru. They, התירו, hitiiru, people, they didn't
know who but they assumed it was under his authority. Let's take
a look. אמרו, Amru, they said, מי ילך ויודיעו, mi yelech veyodio,
who will go and inform him? Now it's interesting, inform him of
what? But we'll see that what it means is that, yeah, inform
him that we oppose this sort of talk to him about this
פסק psak and so on. אמרו להם, Amru lahem, so רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua said, אני אילך, ani eilech, I will go. ואחריו מי,
Veacharav mi, and who will follow him? Because they figured we needed
a couple, we needed a couple of people. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah. ואחריו מי, Veacharav mi, and after him who?
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, הלכו ועמדו על פתח ביתו. Halchu veamdu
al petach beito. They went and they stood by his doorway. Now
the מהרש"א Maharsha reminds us that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is the
אב בית דין, av beit din, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah is the נשיא, nasi, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is
more of the commoner. And nevertheless, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was first
because even though he was the אב בית דין, av beit din,
which was second in command to the נשיא, nasi, we'll see he
was the oldest of them and the one that actually was a
colleague of דוסא בן הרכינס, Dosa ben Horkinas, and we'll see that
that will actually play out in this story. Okay, הלכו ועמדו על
פתח ביתו. halchu veamdu al petach beito. They stood by the opening
of his door. נכנסה שפחתו, Nichnesa shifchato, so his maidservant, רבי דוסא
בן הרכינס' Rabbi Dosa ben Horkinas maidservant came in ואמרה לו, veamra
lo, and said to him, רבי, חכמי ישראל באים אצלך. Rebbi, chachmei
Yisrael baim etzlecha. Rebbi, you should know that some of the great
sages are coming to you. So אמר לה, amar la, he said
to her, יכנסו, yikanesu, let them come in. ונכנסו, Venichnasu, and they
came in. תפסו לרבי יהושע, Tafsu leRabbi Yehoshua, they, again, this is
plural language, I don't and I don't get the language of תפסו.
tafsu. They grabbed רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, והושיבוהו על מטה של זהב,
vehoshibuhu al mita shel zahav, and made him sit on a golden
couch. Maybe he didn't want to accept the כבוד, kavod, they forced
him to. Okay, now the reason again they started with רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua is because he, as we're going to see, was the
oldest of them and the colleague of רבי דוסא בן הרכינס. Rabbi
Dosa ben Horkinas. So אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him,
רבי, אמור לתלמידך אחר וישב. Rebbi, emor letalmidcha acher veyeshev. Rebbi, tell
your other student that he can sit. So obviously אמר לו, amar
lo, who is he? מי הוא? Mi hu? Again, either he wasn't
seeing them at all or he was just barely making them out.
He said, you know we have other, I have other students here,
you have other great rabbis, allow them to sit. So who is
he? מי הוא? Mi hu? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah. אמר, ויש לו בן לעזריה חברנו? Amar, veyesh lo ben leAzaryah
chaveireinu? What? Does Azaryah our friend have a son? So, you know,
obviously he was of the older generation and he wasn't even aware
of the existence of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah,
certainly not about where he, you know, what his status in society.
קרא עליו המקרא הזה, Kara alav hamikra haze, he said about himself
apparently this פסוק. pasuk. נער הייתי גם זקנתי, Naar hayiti gam zakanti,
I was young and now I am old. Obviously right now he's
old. ויהי כי זקן יצחק ותכהין עיניו מראות. Vayehi ki zaken Yitzchak
vatichhena einav merot. Once in a while not being able to identify
who is who, etc. נער הייתי גם זקנתי ולא ראיתי צדיק נעזב
וזרעו מבקש לחם. Naar hayiti gam zakanti velo raiti tzadik neezav vezaro
mevakesh lachem. I've never saw a righteous person abandoned, which is presumably
Azaryah, and his son seeking out bread. Now the מהרש"א Maharsha points
out that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah was very
wealthy, he was from the נשיא. nasi. his house, so that's what
it means that obviously they're doing very well for himself and his
father did very well for himself and they've always, you know, so
that's ולא ראיתי צדיק נעזב, V'lo ra'iti tzaddik ne'ezav, but one also
certainly imagines that there's a play here on לא ראיתי, Lo ra'iti,
right? I'm not seeing his son, okay? So I didn't see the
צדיק נעזב, tzaddik ne'ezav, but I didn't see the son. Anyway, okay,
so anyway, so he so obviously now of course the other thing
to realize here which makes this story also more poignant is it
means that until this time he had yet to been introduced to
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria and even when the
maidservant comes in and says oh רבי, Rebbe, the חכמים chachamim at
the door, it sounds like nobody had been visiting him, right? So,
you know, so it's interesting. Here's the guy that you've been ignoring,
nobody's been visiting him, rather to just, you know, for social reasons
to learn from him, to talk תורה Torah with him, and he
goes and gives a renegade פסק psak and now you want to
engage him like well, you know, if he wasn't showing up to
the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, maybe you should have been visiting him
and engaging him before this and some of this wouldn't have happened.
So anyway, so he says, no, זרעו zaro is the זרעו zaro
of עזריה, Azaria, so it's רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaria. Oh, I don't know. Okay, well again the מהרש"א Maharsha says
that they were very well-to-do. Oh, maybe, that's cute. לחם Lechem is
תורה, Torah, that's cute, he never came here to be מבקש לחם,
mevakesh lechem, that's a nice ווארט. vort. Okay. Actually it seems like
it had been given 50 years earlier. What? That רבי דוסא Rabbi
Dosa lived a long time, the פסק psak could have been given
50 years earlier. Oh, no, but it sounds like they were reacting
immediately. תפסו והושיבו על מיטה של זהב, Tafsu ve'hoshiva al mita shel
zahav, fine, so they took hold of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaria and they made him sit on the gold, gold
couch. אמר ליה Amar lei רבי, Rebbe, so then he again presumably
it's once again what's his name רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, his colleague,
said to him רבי, Rabbi, אמר לתלמידך אחר ישב, amar letalmidecha acher
yeshev, tell your other student that he may sit. אמר ליה Amar
lei ומי הוא, umi hu, who is this other student? עקיבא בן
יוסף, Akiva ben Yosef, it's עקיבא בן יוסף. Akiva ben Yosef. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so he said to him אתה הוא עקיבא בן
יוסף, ata hu Akiva ben Yosef, you are the great עקיבא בן
יוסף Akiva ben Yosef ששמך הולך מסוף העולם ועד סופו, she'shimcha holech
misof ha'olam ve'ad sofo, that your name goes from one end of
the world to the next? So you're oh my God, so you're
such an amazing רבי, Rebbe you have such an amazing reputation. Again
he didn't know the father, right? So it's more and more distant
from him. But he had heard about his reputation. שב בני שב,
Shev beni shev, sit my son sit, כמותך ירבו בישראל, kemotecha yirbu
be'Yisrael, there should be many of
you among the Jewish people. Notice though he didn't get to go
on a gold couch. מהרש"א Maharsha says because he didn't know him,
didn't know the family, he wasn't like, you know, he wasn't from
the inner circle, but he still told him to sit. Okay. And
he wasn't a נשיא, Nasi, he wasn't an אב בית דין, Av
Beit Din, you know, he was a commoner. What? Yeah. Yeah. I
remember back in high school my רבי was once talking about this
גמרא Gemara and he'd say how many gold couches did he have?
Okay, anyway, all right, anyway, okay, התחילו מסבבים אותו בהלכות, hitchilu mesavvevim
oto be'halachot, they surrounded him with הלכות. halachot. Okay, so meaning that
they got him into a conversation, they didn't go straight to this
question, they didn't want him to feel attacked and defensive. So they
started שמוזינג shmoozing in תורה Torah and had a lot of discussion.
מסבבים אותו בהלכות, Mesavvevim oto be'halachot, עד שהגיעו לצרת הבת, ad she'higgi'u
letzarat habat, and finally after a while they came to the discussion
of the צרת הבת. tzarat habat. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said
to him צרת הבת מהו? tzarat habat mahu? What's the story about
a צרת הבת? tzarat habat? So אמר להם amar lahem he said
to them מחלוקת בית שמאי ובית הלל, machloket Beit Shammai ve'Beit Hillel,
it's a מחלוקת בית שמאי ובית הלל. machloket Beit Shammai ve'Beit Hillel.
So they said to him הלכה כדברי מי? halacha k'divrei mi? And
who do we פסקן pasken like, right? אמר להם amar lahem he
said to them הלכה כבית הלל. halacha k'Beit Hillel. We rule like
בית הלל. Beit Hillel. אמרו לו Amru lo they said to him
הלוא משמך אמרו הלכה כבית שמאי, halo mishimcha amru halacha k'Beit Shammai,
but you have it's been reported that you've ruled like בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, that you allowed a case of יבום yibum with צרת
הבת? tzarat habat? So, and they knew he wasn't being defensive because,
you know, they had basically been שמוזינג shmoozing with him, it was
all theoretical and they he genuinely פסקנ'ס paskens like בית הלל Beit
Hillel so what's this we're hearing that you're פסקנינג paskening like בית
שמאי? Beit Shammai? אמר להם Amar lahem he said דוסא שמעתם או
בן הורקנוס שמעתם? Dosa shematem o ben Horkenos shematem? In the report
did you hear them say רבי דוסא בן הורקנוס Rabbi Dosa ben
Horkenos allowed it or did you hear them say בן הורקנוס ben
Horkenos allowed it? So אמרו ליה amru lei they said to him
חיי רבי chayei Rebbe by your life סתם שמענו stam shamanu it
was just בן הורקנוס, ben Horkenos, more general, we didn't hear them
say רבי דוסא בן הורקנוס. Rabbi Dosa ben Horkenos. אמר להם Amar
lahem to them ah that explains it. אח קטן יש לי Ach
katan yesh li I have a younger brother בכור שטן הוא bechor
satan hu which is a fascinating phrase. He's a satanic child. Okay
so some Soncino translated this as a daredevil. רש"י Rashi basically says
somebody that basically just, you know, does not care about other people's
opinions and very strong-willed. Okay, but obviously a bit of a of
a troublemaker and a, you know, and someone who acts completely independently.
ויונתן שמו Ve'Yonatan shemo and his name is יונתן. Yonatan. So actually
it rhymes, right? קטן, Katan, שטן, satan, יונתן. Yonatan. והוא מתלמידי שמאי
Ve'hu mittalmidei Shammai he is of the students of שמאי Shammai and
he's and he is the one that gave the פסק, psak, not
me. והיזהרו בו Ve'hizzaharu bo but והיזהרו בו ve'hizzaharu bo be careful
if you want to challenge him שלא יקפח אתכם בהלכות shelo yikapach
etchem be'halachot that he doesn't sort of overwhelm you with הלכות, halachot,
that he don't don't think he's going to be easy to take
on. לפי שעמו שלוש מאות תשובות בצרת הבת, Lefi she'immo shalosh me'ot
teshuvot be'tzarat habat, he has 300 answers to why a צרת הבת
tzarat habat is is allowed and you do יבום. yibum. So it's
not so don't think you can just easily challenge him. שהיא מותרת.
She'hi mutteret. אבל מעיד אני עלי שמים. Aval me'id ani alai shamayim.
Apart, I testify on me heaven and earth, שעל מדוכה זו ישב
חגי הנביא she-al maducha zo yashav chagai ha-navi on this like a
grinding stone, right, on this large stone which was used as a
seat or was a seat shaped that way, says on this seat
sat חגי הנביא Chagai ha-Navi and he testified about three things. Number
one, צרת הבת אסורה, tzarat ha-bat asura, the צרת הבת tzarat ha-bat
is forbidden, okay, you do not do יבום yibum with צרת הבת.
tzarat ha-bat. Number two, עמוני ומואבי מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית Ammoni u-Moavi
measrin maaser ani be-sheviit and they receive... number two, Ammon and Moav
who live right trans-Jordan, not in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so some
of the laws of תרומות terumot and מעשרות maasrot apply rabbinically, but
nevertheless what happens is during a שמיטה shmita year like this year,
right, this would be the irony that in a שמיטה shmita year
it's supposed to be good for the עניים aniyim because they get
to eat all the food. Of course if nobody's planting then there's
not too much food for the עניים aniyim to have. So Ammon
and Moav actually what they the rabbis said to make the עניים
aniyim have what to live off of in שמיטה, shmita, you gotta
love the irony of that, in שמיטה shmita was one of the
hardest years for the עניים aniyim because of what they did in
order to have them something to live off of, they said Ammon
and Moav who are, you know, who are working the land in
שמיטה, shmita, so they both on the one hand they work the
land, on the other hand they give מעשר maaser because it had
a quasi ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael status rabbinically, and the מעשר maaser
that they should give should be מעשר עני. maaser ani. So therefore
the עניים aniyim will have what to live off of in the
שמיטה, shmita, that's עמוני ומואבי מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית. Ammoni u-Moavi measrin
maaser ani be-sheviit. And number three, ומקבלים גרים מן הקרדוים ומן התרמודים.
u-mekablim gerim min ha-Karduim u-min ha-Tarmudim. You can accept גרים geirim from
these nations, the הקרדוים Karduim and the התרמודים Tarmudim where they're just
non-Jews, we're not afraid apparently there was some concern that it might
have been cases about ישראל ממזרים, Yisrael mamzerim, no, they're just non-Jews
and therefore we can accept גרים. geirim. Okay now let's just pause
for a moment about that idea. We're normally not supposed to use
a נביא Navi to פסקן pasken הלכה. halacha. But what it seems
here is not that he's saying God told me, it seems that
חגי Chagai is the link between, right, the בית ראשון Bayit Rishon
period and the בית שני Bayit Sheni period, right, he's the last
of the נביאים, Neviim, the ones that came back from בבל Bavel
and so on. And it seems that what he's doing is he's
just being a sort of like עדות, edut, he's just giving a
report on practices, on traditions, not he's giving a נבואה. nevuah. Particularly
the last thing about the status of different nations and whether they
are ממזרים mamzerim or are they non-Jews, what's their story. The idea
of עמוני ומואבי מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית Ammoni u-Moavi measrin maaser ani
be-sheviit whether that appears in ידיים, Yadayim, it even uses the phrase
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai which isn't literal obviously because it's
rabbinic, but it means that it's a long-standing tradition. And then that's
also interesting because when we've been beginning the discussion of צרת ערווה,
tzarat ervah, the question we raised is, is this something that really
is being derived from the פסוקים pesukim or was there just a
tradition about צרת ערווה? tzarat ervah? So at least what רבן אלעזר
בן עזריה Rabban Elazar ben Azariah said, I mean רבי דוסא בן
הרכינס Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinas is saying is, if we were to
debate it theoretically based on proofs, you could have come up to
the position of בית שמאי Beit Shammai that צרת הערווה tzarat ha-ervah
should be, I mean there should be a מצוות יבום, mitzvath yibum,
why I mean come on, it's not clear in the פסוקים pesukim
that a צרת ערווה tzarat ervah is exempt from יבום. yibum. But
the story is that's all very nice if you're dealing with proofs,
but we have a tradition that צרת ערווה tzarat ervah is not
חייב chayav in יבום, yibum, is אסורה לאחים, asura le-achim, and I
know that tradition goes all the way back to חגי. Chagai. So
again it's an interesting question about tradition as opposed to derivation from
פסוקים pesukim and the role of a נביא, Navi, here he's not
doing it as נבואה nevuah but as a somebody who is מוסר
moseir the tradition, right, when משה קיבל תורה מסיני ויהושע יהושע לזקנים
וזקנים לנביאים Moshe kibel Torah mi-Sinai u-Yehoshua Yehoshua li-Zkenim u-Zkenim li-Neviim etc.,
there the נביאים Neviim are not נבואה, nevuah, there the נביאים Neviim
are just those that are passing on the tradition, yes. Wasn't חגי
Chagai one of the founders of the אנשי כנסת הגדולה? Anshei Knesset
HaGedolah? Yes, that is true as well. Thank you. According to חז"ל
Chazal he was also part of the אנשי כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Knesset
HaGedolah. So it's interesting, a, so clearly a, that frame that one
of the positions of the בית הלל Beit Hillel of צרת הבת
tzarat ha-bat might be based less on פסוקים pesukim and more on
tradition, but that all of these three things of חגי Chagai are
presumably things related to things that we have traditions about. Okay, so
anyway but don't think you're going to win him in a fight.
תנא. Tana. So it's taught in a ברייתא, baraita, כשיכנסו נכנסו בפתח
אחד, keshenikhnesu nikhnesu be-fetach echad, when they came in they came in
one door, כשיצאו יצאו בשלושה פתחים, kesheyatzu yatzu bi-shlosha petachim, when they
left they left in three doors. Now why exactly is not clear.
תוספות Tosafot says it's because, well let's read the story and then
I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot says about why they left in
three doors. פגע בו ברבי עקיבא. paga bo be-Rabbi Akiva. Now רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva encountered this brother, יונתן בן דוסא Yonatan ben Dosa
encountered רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אקשי ליה. akshi leh. So he challenged
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and he with all of his proofs that
צרת הבת tzarat ha-bat should be allowed. ואוקמיה ve-ukmey and he basically
literally stood רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva up like he made him stand,
meaning רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had no response. So he, not that
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva conceded, but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was not
able to disprove any of the proofs. אמר לו. amar lo. So
יונתן Yonatan won with רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, like when do you
ever hear anybody beating רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in a battle of
wits? So יונתן Yonatan said to him, אמר לו amar lo said
to him, אתה הוא עקיבא ששמך הולך מסוף העולם ועד סופו, ata
hu Akiva she-shimkha holekh mi-sof ha-olam ve-ad sofo, right, which is what
his brother said, are you עקיבא Akiva whose fame goes from one
end of the world to the next? So he said, אשריך שזכית
לשם ועדיין לא הגעת לרועה. ashreikha she-zakhita le-shem ve-adayin lo higata le-roeh.
Whoa, talk about a cutting insult! You should be praised, just such
a trem- amazing reputation and name, and you're not even worthy of
being like a shepherd or whatever, a cowherd. So a little different
than
what his brother said, כמיך ירבו בישראל, K'mecha yirbu b'Yisrael, he said
you should be very fortunate you have such a good reputation, seeing
as what a poor Talmudic scholar you are. So pretty harsh. So
אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva, so Rabbi Akiva responded,
ואפילו רועה צאן, V'afilu roeh tzon, you're right, I'm not even worthy
of being a shepherd. So it's a good way of a little
undercutting it to concede the point. The מהרש״א Maharsha says that he's
talking about that it's like a little, tries to see it as
a battle of wits, that he wants to say that the רועה
צאן roeh tzon refers to Moshe and I have this is a
מסורה mesorah from going all the way back to משה רבינו, Moshe
Rabbeinu, but anyway, it's certainly, certainly that's a דרש drash on this.
Okay, anyway, so Yonatan may be proved the point by proofs or
at least stood his position by proofs and nevertheless there's this מסורה
mesorah from חגי. Chagai. Now by the way, take a look at
the תוספות, Tosafot, יצאו בשלושה פתחים, yatzu b'ghimmel petachim, תוספות Tosafot says
שלא ימצאו כולם יחד ויקפחם בהלכות ויצטרכו לקבוע הלכה כמותו. shelo yimtzu
kulam yachad v'yikapchem b'halachot v'yitztarchu likboa halacha k'moto. They were afraid that
all three of them would encounter him at once and if he
would win the argument against all three of them, then they couldn't
not פסקן pasken that way. But if he only won the argument
against one of them, the other two could say well, we weren't
there, I'm sure we would have had a better answer and they
don't have to feel that they have to concede the point. אי
נמי, Ee nami, יצאו בשלושה פתחים כדי שימצאוהו וישמעו תשובתו. yatzu b'ghimmel
petachim k'dei she-yimtzauhu v'yishmeu teshuvato. They wanted to spread out so one
of them at least could find him and engage him. So it's
quite interesting, were they looking to engage him or they were looking
to at least not engage him in a way that they would
feel they would have to concede the point. So fascinating other פרשה
parsha to the story about צרת הבת. tzarat ha-bat. Okay, now let's,
now the גמרא Gemara is going to go back and talk about
the other two things that we have as a מסורה mesorah from
חגי. Chagai. Let's take a look. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo
Rabbi Akiva, עמון ומואב מעשרין מעשר עני בשביעית, Ammon u-Moav m'asrin ma'aser
ani b'shevi'it, דאמר מר, d'amar mar, because we teach, הרבה כרכים כיבשו
עולי מצרים ולא כיבשו עולי בבל, harbeh krachim kibshu olei Mitzrayim v'lo
kibshu olei Bavel, that there were many cities actually in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael proper, this was outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but
even in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael proper there were many cities that
were conquered when they came up from Egypt at the time of
יהושע Yehoshua but were not reconquered in the time of עזרא, Ezra,
and it goes by the second, their status of קדושה kedusha goes
by the second entry. וקדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה לעתיד לבוא,
Uk'dusha rishona kidsha l'shata v'lo kidsha l'atid lavo, the first sanctity in
the time of יהושע Yehoshua was not for future times and therefore
it goes by whether they would be resanctified in the second בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they were not. Now why were they not?
And this is the key point because this is ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, this isn't עמון ומואב, Ammon u-Moav, but here's the key point:
some cities were intentionally not resanctified, והניחום, v'henichum, and they were left,
כדי שיסמכו עליהם עניים בשביעית, k'dei she-yismachu aleihem aniyim b'shevi'it, so that
the עניים aniyim should have what to live off of on שמיטה.
Shmita. Again it's particularly ironic that שמיטה Shmita is hard for the
עניים aniyim because nobody's growing anything. So they left cities that could
grow on שמיטה Shmita so the עניים aniyim would have what they've,
and also by the way, רש״י Rashi points out they'd also hire
the עניים aniyim to work the fields within those cities. Okay, so
that's, and the same way they did that in those cities, that
was also the status of עמון ומואב Ammon u-Moav that had some
תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot but it wasn't real קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushat
Eretz Yisrael and therefore they didn't apply שביעית shevi'it and they allowed
the עניים aniyim were sustained from that and also from the fact
that they made it מעשר עני ma'aser ani and not מעשר שני.
ma'aser sheni. Now the last, the third הלכה, halacha, ומקבלים גרים מן
הקרדוים ומן התרמודיים. u-mikablim gerim min ha-Karduyim u-min ha-Tarmudiyim. איני? Eini? Is
this really true? והתני רמי בר יחזקאל, v'hatani Rami bar Yechezkel, אין
מקבלים גרים מן הקרדוים. ein mikablim gerim min ha-Karduyim. אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, כרתיים Kartuyim איתמר. itmar. No, when he says you
can't take גרים gerim from them, that there's a concern of ממזרים
mamzerim and not non-Jews, it's not the קרדוים, Karduyim, it's the כרתיים.
Kartuyim. כדאמרי אינשי, K'd'amrei inshi, כרתיים פסולים. Kartuyim psulim. Apparently that was
a phrase, oh, you invalid כרתיים, Kartuyim, like כרתיים פסולים, Kartuyim psulim,
it rhymed. So that's a label people used to indicate if something
is פסול, pasul, invalid, and that's what we're talking about, כרתיים Kartuyim
not קרדוים. Karduyim. ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika d'amrei, תני רמי בר יחזקאל, tani
Rami bar Yechezkel, אין מקבלים גרים מן הכרתיים. ein mikablim gerim min
ha-Kartuyim. Some originally say that he said מן הכרתיים min ha-Kartuyim you
cannot take גרים. gerim. מאי לאו היינו כרתיים היינו קרדוים? Mai lav
hainu Kartuyim hainu Karduyim? Isn't it the same? אמר רב אשי, Amar
Rav Ashi, לא, Lo, no it's not the same, כרתי לחוד וקרדוי
לחוד, Kartay lachud v'Karduy lachud, they're different. כרתי Kartay is different than
קרדוי. Karduy. כדאמרי אינשי, K'd'amrei inshi, כרתי פסילי. Kartay psiley. People say
כרתי Kartay is פסול pasul but not, so it's a phrase used
כרתיים Kartuyim specifically not קרדוים. Karduyim. ורבי יוחנן וסביא דאמרי תרווייהו, V'Rabbi
Yochanan v'Savya d'amri tarvaihu, now Rabbi Yochanan and סביא Savya both say,
interesting name סביא, Savya, אין מקבלים גרים מן התרמודיים, ein mikablim gerim
min ha-Tarmudiyim, you do not accept גרים gerim from התרמודיים, ha-Tarmudiyim, as
opposed to the tradition of חגי Chagai that you do. ומי אמר
רבי יוחנן הכי? U-mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Did he really say
this? והתנן, v'hatnan, don't we teach, כל הכתמים הבאים מן הרקם טהורים,
kol ha-ktamim ha-baim min ha-Rekem tehorim, all stains that you find on
cloths that might have come from menstruating women who were menses, women
who were menstruating, but it's only a problem if they come from
Jewish women, not from non-Jewish women. Non-Jewish women, their stains are not
טמא. tamei. So if they come from רקם Rekem they're טהור tehor
because in רקם Rekem are non-Jews. רבי יהודה מטמא, Rabbi Yehuda mtamei,
Rabbi Yehuda says no, if they come from רקם Rekem they're טמא.
tamei. מפני שהן גירים וטועים Mipnei shehen geirim veto'im because they are
converts but they think they're non-Jews. So they, but it actually is
a city of converts and therefore their stains are טמא. Tamei. וטהורים
Vetohorim מבין עובדי כוכבים, mibein ovdei kochavim, stains that come from non-Jews,
טהורים. tehorim. Those are, you know, it's clearly non-Jews, those are טהור.
tahor. ובעינן בה Vavinan bah and we asked on this, we'll just
do one more minute. קא פסיק ותני, Ka pasik vetanei, the Mishnah
is categorical. מבין עובדי כוכבים, Mibein ovdei kochavim, anything that comes from
any non-Jews is טהור. tahor. אפילו מתרמוד, Afilu mitarmod, presumably even if
it comes from this place תרמוד Tarmod which was clearly a place
they had questions about. So it seems that since it doesn't distinguish
that place, that even תרמוד Tarmod is considered to be non-Jews. It's
not a concern about about ממזרים mamzerim or the like. ואמר רבי
יוחנן, Va'amar Rebbi Yochanan, זאת אומרת מקבלים גרים מתרמוד, zot omeret mikablim
geirim mitarmod, and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan explicitly says that. So how
could we have another רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that says you don't
accept גרים geirim from תרמוד? Tarmod? וכי תימא זאת ולא סבירא ליה,
Vechi teima zot velo svira lei, unless you say רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan says that's what this Mishnah implies but we don't hold by
this Mishnah? ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה. Va'amar Rebbi Yochanan halacha
kestam mishnah. We say רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says we rule like
a סתם משנה. stam mishnah. So we have one tradition that רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says you accept גרים geirim from תרמוד Tarmod and
the other tradition that says you don't accept גרים geirim from תרמוד.
Tarmod. What's the story? So the גמרא Gemara says אמוראי נינהו ואליבא
דרבי יוחנן. Amorai ninhu va'aliba deRebbi Yochanan. So it's a debate of
אמוראים Amoraim in the name of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan whether רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan felt תרמוד Tarmod was a problematic place or not
a problematic place. And we will pick up tomorrow to see what
would have been the problems with תרמוד, Tarmod, why is it being
debated, what are the issues.